forest. Chapter 8. Flies and spiders.
They walked in single file. The entrance to the path was like a sort of arch
leading into a gloomy tunnel made by two great trees that lent together, too old
and strangled with ivy and hung with lyken to bear more than a few blackened
leaves. The path itself was narrow and wound in and out among the trunks. Soon
the light at the gate was like a little bright hole far behind, and the quiet
was so deep that their feet seemed to thump along while all the trees leaned
over them and listened. As their eyes became used to the dimness, they could
see a little way to either side in the sort of darkened green glimmer.
Occasionally a slender beam of sun that had the luck to slip in through some
opening in the leaves far above, and still more luck in not being caught in
the tangled boughs and matted twigs beneath, stabbed down thin and bright
before them. But this was seldom, and it soon ceased altogether.
There were black squirrels in the wood.
As Bilbo's sharp, inquisitive eyes got used to seeing things, he could catch
glimpses of them whisking off the path and scuttling behind tree trunks. There
were queer noises, too. Grunts, scufflings, and hurrings in the
undergrowth, and among the leaves that lay piled endlessly thick in places on
the forest floor. But what made the noises he could not see? The nastiest
things they saw were the cobwebs, dark, dense cobwebs with threads
extraordinarily thick, often stretched from tree to tree, or tangled in the
lower branches on either side of them.
There were none stretched across the path, but whether because some magic
kept it clear, or for what other reason, they could not guess.
It was not long before they grew to hate the forest as hardily as they had hated
the tunnels of the goblins, and it seemed to offer even less hope of any
ending, but they had to go on and on, long after they were sick for a sight of
the sun and of the sky, and longed for the feel of wind on their faces. There
was no movement of air down under the forest roof, and it was everlastingly
still and dark and stuffy. Even the dwarves felt it, who were used to
tunneling, and lived at times for long whiles without the light of the sun. But
the hobbit, who liked holes to make a house in, but not to spend summer days
in, felt that he was being slowly suffocated.
The nights were the worst. It then became pitch dark. Not what you call
pitch dark, but really pitch, so black that you really could see nothing. Bilbo
tried flapping his hand in front of his nose, but he could not see it at all.
Well, perhaps it is not true to say that they could see nothing. They could see
eyes. They slept all closely, huddled together, and took it in turns to watch.
And when it was Bilbo's turn, he would see gleams in the darkness around him.
And sometimes pairs of yellow or red or green eyes would stare at him from a
little distance, and then slowly fade and disappear and slowly shine out again
in another place, and sometimes they would glean down from the branches just
above him, and that was most terrifying.
But the eyes that he liked the least were horrible, pale, bulbous sort of
eyes. Insect eyes, he thought, not animal eyes, only they are much too big.
Although it was not yet very cold, they tried lighting watchfires at night, but
they soon gave that up. It seemed to bring hundreds and hundreds of eyes all
around them, though the creatures, whatever they were, were careful never
to let their body show in the little flicker of the flames. Worse still, he
brought thousands of dark gray and black moths, some nearly as big as your hand,
flapping and worring round their ears.
They could not stand that, nor the huge bats, black as a top hat, either. So
they gave up fires and sat at night and dozed in the enormous uncanny darkness.
All this went on for what seemed to the hobbit ages upon ages, and he was always
hungry, for they were extremely careful with their provisions. Even so, as days
followed days, and still the forest seemed just the same, they began to get
anxious. The food would not last forever. It was in fact already
beginning to get low. They tried shooting at the squirrels, and they
wasted many arrows before they managed to bring one down on the path. But when
they roasted it, it proved horrible to taste, and they shot no more squirrels.
They were thirsty, too, for they had none too much water, and in all the time
they had seen neither spring nor stream.
This was their state when one day they found their path blocked by a running
water. It flowed fast and strong, but not very wide right across the way, and
it was black or looked it in the gloom.
It was well that Beern had warned them against it, or they would have drunk
from it, whatever its color, and filled some of their emptied skins at its bank.
As it was, they only thought of how to cross it without wetting themselves in
its water. There had been a bridge of water across, but it had rotted and
fallen, leaving only the broken posts near the bank. Bilbo, kneeling on the
brink, and peering forward, cried, "There is a boat against the far bank
now. Why couldn't it have been this side?" "How far away do you think it
is?" asked Thoren, for by now they knew Bilbo had the sharpest eyes among them.
"Not at all far. I shouldn't think above 12 yd." "1 yard? I should have thought
it was 30 at least, but my eyes don't see as well as they used a hundred years
ago. Still 12 yards is as good as a mile. We can't jump it, and we dare try
to wade or swim.
Can any of you throw a rope? What's the good of that? The boat is sure to be
tied up, even if we could hook it, which I doubt. I don't believe it is tied,
said Bilbo. Though of course I can't be sure in this light, but it looks to me
as if it was just drawn up on the bank which is low just there where the path
goes down into the water. Dory is the strongest, but Feele is the youngest and
still has the best sight, said Thorne.
Come here, Feelely, and see if you can see the boat Mr. Baggins is talking
about. Fely thought he could, so when he had stared a long while to get an idea
of the direction, the others brought him a rope. They had several with them, and
on the end of the longest, they fastened one of the large iron hooks they had
used for catching their packs to the straps about their shoulders.
Feelely took this in his hand, balanced it for a moment, and then flung it
across the stream. Splash! It fell in the water. Not far enough, said Bilbo,
who was peering forward. A couple of feet and you would have dropped it onto
the boat. Try again. I don't suppose the magic is strong enough to hurt you if
you just touch a bit of wet rope. Philly picked up the hook when he had drawn it
back rather doubtfully all the same.
This time he throat with great strength.
Steady, said Bilbo. You have thrown it right into the wood on the other side.
Now draw it back gently.
Philly hold the rope back slowly and after a while Bilbo said carefully. It
is lying on the boat. Let's hope the hook will catch. It did. The rope went
taut and Philly pulled in vain. Killy came to his help and then o and glowing.
They tugged and tugged and suddenly they all fell over on their backs.
Bilbo was on the lookout, however, caught the rope and with a piece of
stick fended off the little black boat as it came rushing across the stream.
"Help!" he shouted, and Balon was just in time to seize the boat before it
floated off down the current. "It was tied after all," said he, looking at the
snapped painter that was still dangling from it. "That was a good pull, my lads,
and a good job that our rope was the stronger." "Who crossed first?" asked
Bilbo. I shall, said Thorin. And you will come with me and Philly and Balon.
That's as many as the boat will hold at a time. After that, Killy and Oin and
Gloin and Dory, next Ory and Nori, Beefer and Bofer, and last Dwallan and
Bomb. I'm always last, and I don't like it, said Bombber. It's somebody else's
turn today. You should not be so fat as you are. You must be with the last and
lightest boatload. Don't start grumbling against orders or something bad will
happen to you. There aren't any ores.
How are you going to push the boat back to the far bank? asked the hobbit. Give
me another length of rope and another hook, said Philly. And when they had got
it ready, he cast it into the darkness ahead and as high as he could throw it.
Since it did not fall down again, they saw that it must have stuck in the
branches. "Get in now," said Feelely.
"And one of you haul on the rope that is
stuck in a tree on the other side. One of the others must keep hold of the hook
we used at first, and when we are safe on the other side, he can hook it on,
and you can draw the boat back." In this way, they were all soon on the far bank,
safe across the enchanted stream. Twelyn had just scrambled out with the coiled
rope on his arm, and Bomber, still grumbling, was getting ready to follow
when something bad did happen. There was a flying sound of hooves on the path ahead.
Out of the gloom came suddenly the shape of a flying deer. It charged into the
dwarves and bowled them over, then gathered itself for a leap. high it
sprang and cleared the water with a mighty jump, but it did not reach the
other side in safety. Thoren was the only one who had kept his feet and his
wits. As soon as they had landed, he had bent his bow and fitted an arrow in case
any hidden guardian of the boat appeared. Now he sent a swift and sure
shot into the leaping beast. As it reached the further bank, it stumbled.
The shadows swallowed it up, but they heard the sound of hooves quickly falter
and then go still. Before they could shout in praise of the shot, however, a
dreadful whale from Bilbo put all thoughts of venison out of their minds.
"Bombour has fallen in." "Bombour is drowning," he cried. It was only too
true. Bomb had only one foot on the land when the hut bore down on him and sprang
over him. He had stumbled, thrusting the boat away from the bank, and then
toppled back into the dark water, his hands slipping off the slimy roots at
the edge, while the boat span slowly off and disappeared. They could still see
his hood above the water when they ran to the bank. Quickly, they flung a rope
with a hook towards him, his hand caught it, and they pulled him to the shore. He
was drenched from hair to boots, of course, but that was not the worst. When
they laid him on the bank, he was already fast asleep, with one hand
clutching the rope so tight that they could not get it from his grasp, and
fast asleep he remained in spite of all they could do.
They were still standing over him, cursing their ill luck and Bombber's
clumsiness, and lamenting the loss of the boat, which made it impossible for
them to go back and look for the heart, when they became aware of the dim
blowing of horns and the wood, and the sound as of dogs baying far off. Then
they all fell silent, and as they sat, it seemed they could hear the noise of a
great hunt going by to the north of the path, though they saw no sign of it.
There they sat for a long while and did not dare to make a move. Bomber slept on
with a smile on his fat face, as if he no longer cared for all the troubles
that vexed them. Suddenly, on the path ahead appeared some white deer, a hind
and fawns as snowy white as the heart had been dark. They glimmered in the
shadows. Before a thorn could cry out, three of the dwarves had leaped to their
feet and loosed off arrows from their bows. None seemed to find their mark.
The deer turned and vanished in the trees as silently as they had come, and
in vain the dwarves shot their arrows after them. "Stop! Stop!" shouted Doran,
but it was too late. The excited dwarves had wasted their last arrows, and now
the bows that Bejorn had given them were useless. "They were a gloomy party that
night, and the gloom gathered still deeper on them in the following days.
They had crossed the enchanted stream, but beyond it the path seemed to
straddle on just as before, and in the forest they could see no change. Yet if
they had known more about it, and considered the meaning of the hunt, and
the white deer that had appeared upon their path, they would have known that
they were at last drawing towards the eastern edge, and would soon have come,
if they could have kept up their courage and their hope, to thinner trees and
places where the sunlight came again.
But they did not know this, and they were burdened with the heavy body of
Bombore, which they had to carry along with them as best they could, taking the
wearyome task in turns of four each, while the others shared their packs. If
these had not become all too light in the last few days, they would never have
managed it. But a slumbering and smiling bombore was a poor exchange for packs
filled with food, however heavy. In a few days a time came when there was
practically nothing left to eat or to drink. Nothing wholesome could they see
growing in the wood, only funguses and herbs with pale leaves and unpleasant
smell. About 4 days from the enchanted stream they came to a part where most of
the trees were beaches. They were at first inclined to be cheered by the
change, for here there was no undergrowth and the shadow was not so
deep. There was a greenish light about them, and in places they could see some
distance to either side of the path. Yet the light only showed them endless lines
of straight gray trunks like the pillars of some huge twilight hall. There was a
breath of air and a noise of wind, but it had a sad sound. A few leaves came
rustling down to remind them that outside autumn was coming on. Their feet
ruffled among the dead leaves of countless other autumns that drifted
over the banks of the path from the deep red carpets of the forest. Still Bomber
slept, and they grew very weary. At times they heard disquing laughter.
Sometimes there was singing in the distance, too. The laughter was the
laughter of fair voices, not of goblins, and the singing was beautiful, but it
sounded eerie and strange, and they were not comforted. Rather, they hurried on
from those parts with what strength they had left. Two days later they found
their path going downwards, and before long they were in a valley filled almost
entirely with a mighty growth of oaks.
Is there no end to this oursed forest?
said Thorin. Somebody must climb a tree and see if he can get his head above the
roof and have a look round. The only way is to choose the tallest tree that
overhangs the path. Of course, somebody meant Bilbo. They chose him because to
be of any use the climber must get his head above the topmost leaves, and so he
must be light enough for the highest and slenderest branches to bear him. Poor
Mr. Baggins had never had much practice in climbing trees, but they hoisted him
up into the lowest branches of an enormous oak that grew right out into
the path, and up he had to go as best he could. He pushed his way through the
tangled twigs with many a slap in the eye. He was greened and grimed from the
old bark of the greater boughs. More than once he slipped and caught himself
just in time, and at last, after a dreadful struggle in a difficult place,
where there seemed to be no convenient branches at all, he got near the top.
All the time he was wondering whether there were spiders in the tree, and how
he was going to get down again, except by falling. In the end, he poked his
head above the roof of leaves, and then he found spiders, all right, but they
were only small ones of ordinary size, and they were after the butterflies.
Bilbo's eyes were nearly blinded by the light. He could hear the dwarves
shouting up at him from far below, but he could not answer, only hold on and
blink. The sun was shining brilliantly, and it was a long while before he could
bear it. When he could, he saw all around him a sea of dark green, ruffled
here and there by the breeze, and there were everywhere hundreds of butterflies.
I expect they were a kind of purple emperor, a butterfly that loves the tops
of oak woods, but these were not purple at all. They were a dark, dark, velvety
black without any markings to be seen.
He looked at the black emperors for a long time, and enjoyed the feel of the
breeze in his hair and on his face, but at length the cries of the dwarves, who
were now simply stamping with impatience down below, reminded him of his real
business. It was no good. Gaze, as much as he might, he could see no end to the
trees and the leaves in any direction.
His heart, that had been lightened by the sight of the sun and the feel of the
wind, sank back into his toes. There was no food to go back to down below.
Actually, as I have told you, they were not far off the edge of the forest, and
if Bilbo had had the sense to see it, the tree that he had climbed, though it
was tall in itself, was standing near the bottom of a wide valley, so that
from its top the tree seemed to swell up all round like the edges of a great
ball, and he could not expect to see how far the forest lasted. Still he did not
see this, and he climbed down full of despair. He got to the bottom again at
last, scratched, hot, and miserable, and he could not see anything in the gloom
below when he got there. His report soon made the others as miserable as he was.
The forest goes on forever and ever and ever in all directions. Whatever shall
we do? And what is the use of sending a hobbit? They cried as if it was his
fault. They did not care tuppens about the butterflies and were only made more
angry when he told them of the beautiful breeze which they were too heavy to
climb up and feel. That night they ate their very last scraps and crumbs of
food. And next morning when they woke, the first thing they noticed was that
they were still knowingly hungry, and the next thing was that it was raining,
and that here and there the drip of it was dropping heavily on the forest
floor. That only reminded them that they were also parchingly thirsty without
doing anything to relieve them. You cannot quench a terrible thirst by
standing under giant oaks and waiting for a chance drip to fall on your
tongue. The only scrap of comfort there was came unexpectedly from Bombore.
He woke up suddenly and sat up scratching his head. He could not make
out where he was at all, nor why he felt so hungry, for he had forgotten
everything that had happened since they started their journey that may morning
long ago. The last thing that he remembered was the party at the hobbits
house, and they had great difficulty in making him believe their tale of all the
many adventures they had had. When he heard that there was nothing to eat, he
sat down and wept, for he felt very weak and wobbly in the legs. Why ever did I
wake up? He cried. I was having such beautiful dreams. I dreamed I was
walking in a forest rather like this one, only lit with torches on the trees
and lamps swinging from the branches and fires burning on the ground. And there
was a great feast going on, going on forever. A woodland king was there with
a crown of leaves, and there was a merry singing, and I could not count or
describe the things there were to eat and drink. You need not try, said
Thoren. In fact, if you can't talk about something else, you had better be
silent. We are quite annoyed enough with you as it is. If you hadn't wake up, we
should have left you to your idiotic dreams in the forest. You are no joke to
carry even after weeks of short commons.
There was nothing now to be done but to tighten the belts around their empty
stomachs and hoist their empty sacks and packs and trudge along the track without
any great hope of ever getting to the end before they lay down and died of starvation.
This they did all that day going very slowly and wearily while Bomber kept on
wailing that his legs would not carry him and that he wanted to lie down and
sleep. No you don't, they said, let your legs take their share. We have carried
you far enough. All the same, he suddenly refused to go a step further
and flung himself on the ground. Go on if you must, he said. I'm just going to
lie here and sleep and dream of food if
I can't get it any other way. I hope I never wake up again. At that very
moment, Balon, who was a little way ahead, called out, "What was that?" I
thought I saw a twinkle of light in the forest.
They all looked, and a longish way off, it seemed, they saw a red twinkle in the
dark. Then another, and another sprang out beside it. Even Bombber got up, and
they hurried along then, not caring if it was trolls or goblins. The light was
in front of them, and to the left of the path, and when at last they had drawn
level with it, it seemed plain that torches and fires were burning under the
trees, but a good way off their track.
It looks as if my dreams were coming true, guested Bomber puffing up behind.
He wanted to rush straight off into the wood after the lights. But the others
remembered only too well the warnings of the wizard and of Bejorn.
A feast would be no good if we never got back alive from it, said Thoren. "But
without a feast, we shhat remain alive much longer anyway," said Bomber. And
Bilbo hardily agreed with him. They argued about it backwards and forwards
for a long while until they agreed at length to send out a couple of spies to
creep near the lights and find out more about them. But then they could not
agree on who was to be sent. No one seemed anxious to run the chance of
being lost and never finding his friends again. In the end, in spite of warnings,
hunger decided them because Bumbor kept on describing all the good things that
were being eaten according to his dream in the woodland feast. So they all left
the path and plunged into the forest together. After a good deal of creeping
and crawling, they peered around the trunks and looked into a clearing where
some trees had been felled and the ground leveled. There were many people
there, Elvishlooking folk, all dressed in green and brown, and sitting on saw
rings of the felled trees in a great circle. There was a fire in their midst,
and there were torches fastened to some of the trees round about, but most
splendid sight of all, they were eating and drinking and laughing merrily. The
smell of the roast meats was so enchanting that without waiting to
consult one another, every one of them got up and scrambled forwards into the
ring with the one idea of begging for some food. No sooner had the first
stepped into the clearing than all the lights went out as if by magic. Somebody
kicked the fire and it went up in rockets of glittering sparks and
vanished. They were lost in a completely lightless dark, and they could not even
find one another, not for a long time at any rate. After blundering frantically
in the gloom, falling over logs, bumping crash into trees, and shouting and
calling till they must have waked everything in the forest for miles, at
last they managed to gather themselves in a bundle and count themselves by
touch. By that time they had, of course, quite forgotten in what direction the
path lay, and they were all hopelessly lost, at least till morning. There was
nothing for it but to settle down for the night where they were. They did not
even dare to search on the ground for scraps of food for fear of becoming separated again.
But they had not been lying long, and Bilbo was only just getting drowsy when
Dory, whose turn it was to watch first, said in a loud whisper, "The lights are
coming out again over there, and there are more than ever of them." Up they all
jumped. There, sure enough, not far away, were scores of twinkling lights,
and they heard the voices and the laughter quite plainly. They crept
slowly towards them in a single line, each touching the back of the one in
front. When they got near for and said, "No rushing forward this time. No one is
to stir from hiding till I say I shall send Mr. Baggins alone first to talk to
them. They won't be frightened of him.
What about me of them?
They won't be frightened, right? When they got to the edge of the circle of
lights, they pushed Bilbo suddenly from behind. Before he had time to slip on
his ring, he stumbled forward into the full blaze of the fire and torches. It
was no good. Out went all the lights again, and complete darkness fell. If it
had been difficult collecting themselves before, it was far worse this time, and
they simply could not find the Hobbit.
Every time they counted themselves, it only made 13. They shouted and called,
"Bil Baggins! Hobbit! You dreaded Hobbit! Hi, Hobbit! Confisticate you?
Where are you?" and other things of that sort. But there was no answer.
They were just giving up hope when Dory stumbled across him by sheer luck. In
the dark he fell over what he thought was a log, and he found it was the
hobbit curled up fast asleep. It took a deal of shaking to wake him, and when he
was awake he was not pleased at all. I was having such a lovely dream, he
grumbled, all about having a most gorgeous dinner. Good heavens, he is
gone like barber, they said. Don't tell us about dreams. Dream dinners aren't
any good, and we can't share them. They are the best I am likely to get in this
beastly place," he muttered as he lay down beside the dwarves and tried to go
back to sleep and find his dream again.
But that was not the last of the lights in the forest. Later, when the night
must have been getting old, Killy, who was watching then, came and roused them
all again, saying, "There's a regular blaze of light begun not far away.
Hundreds of torches and many fires must have been lit suddenly and by magic, and
harp to the singing and the harps."
After lying and listening for a while, they found they could not resist the
desire to go nearer and try once more to get help. Up they got again, and this
time the result was disastrous.
The feast that they now saw was greater and more magnificent than before. And at
the head of a long line of feasters sat a woodland king with a crown of leaves
upon his golden hair, very much as Bumper had described the figure in his
dream. The Elvish folk were passing balls from hand to hand and across the
fires, and some were harping, and many were singing. Their gleaming hair was
twined with flowers. Green and white gems glinted on their collars and their
belts, and their faces in their songs were filled with mirth. Loud and clear
and fair were those songs, and outstepped thoren into their midst. Dead
silence fell in the middle of a word.
Out went all light. The fires leaped up in black smokes. Ashes and cinders were
in the eyes of the dwarves, and the wood was filled again with their clamor and
their cries. Bilbo found himself running round and round as he thought, and
calling and calling. Dory, Nori, Ori, Glorin, Philly, Killy, Bomber, Beefer,
Bulfo, Dwallin, Bolin, Thoren, Oakenshield, while people he could not
see or feel were doing the same all around him, with an occasional bilbo,
thrown in, but the cries of the others got steadily further and fainter, and
though after a while it seemed to him they changed to yells and cries for help
in the far distance, all noise at last died right away, and he was left alone
in complete silence and darkness.
That was one of his most miserable moments. But he soon made up his mind
that it was no good trying to do anything till day came with some little
light, and quite useless to go blundering about, tiring himself out
with no hope of any breakfast to revive him. So he sat himself down with his
back to a tree and not for the last time fell to thinking of his far distant
hobbit hole with its beautiful pantries.
He was deep in thoughts of bacon and eggs and toast and butter when he felt
something touch him. Something like a strong sticky string was against his
left hand, and when he tried to move, he found that his legs were already wrapped
in the same stuff, so that when he got up, he fell over. Then the great spider,
who had been busy tying him up while he dozed, came from behind him and came at
him. He could only see the thing's eyes, but he could feel its hairy legs as it
struggled to wind its abominable threads round and round him. It was lucky that
he had come to his senses in time. Soon he would not have been able to move at
all. As it was, he had a desperate fight before he got free. He beat the creature
off with his hands. It was tried to poison him to keep him quiet as small
spiders do to flies until he remembered his sword and drew it out. Then the
spider jumped back and he had time to cut his legs loose. After that it was
his turn to attack. The spider evidently was not used to things that carried such
stings at their sides or it would have hurried away quicker. Bilbo came at it
before it could disappear and stuck it with his sword right in the eyes. Then
it went mad and leaped and danced and flung out its legs in horrible jerks
until he killed it with another stroke.
And then he fell down and remembered nothing more for a long while. There is
the usual dim gray light of the forest day about him when he came to his
senses. The spider lay dead beside him, and his sword blade was stained black.
Somehow the killing of the giant spider all alone by himself in the dark without
the help of the wizard or the dwarves or of anyone else made a great difference
to Mr. Baggins. He felt a different person and much fiercer and bolder in
spite of an empty stomach as he wiped his sword on the grass and put it back
into its sheath. "I will give you a name," he said to it, "and I shall call
you Sting." After that he set out to explore. The forest was grim and silent,
but obviously he had first of all to look for his friends, who were not
likely to be very far off, unless they had been made prisoners by the elves, or
worse things. Bilbo felt that it was unsafe to shout, and he stood a long
while wondering in what direction the path lay, and in what direction he
should go first to look for the dwarves.
An why did we not remember Bern's advice and Gandalf's? He lamented. What a mess
we are in now. We I only wish it was we.
It is horrible being all alone.
In the end he made as good a guess as he could at the direction from which the
cries for help had come in the night, and by luck he was born with a good
share of it. He guessed more or less right, as you will see.
Having made up his mind, he crept along as cleverly as he could.
Hobbits are clever at quietness, especially in woods, as I have already told you.
Also, Bilbo had slipped on his ring before he started. That is why the
spiders neither saw nor heard him coming. He had picked his way stealthily
for some distance, when he noticed a place of dense black shadow ahead of
him, black even for that forest, like a patch of midnight that had never been
cleared away. As he drew nearer, he saw that it was made by spiderw webs, one
behind and over and tangled with another. Suddenly he saw too, that there
were spiders huge and horrible sitting in the branches above him, and ring or
no ring, he trembled with fear, lest they should discover him. Standing
behind a tree, he watched a group of them for some time, and then, in the
silence and stillness of the wood, he realized that these loathsome creatures
were speaking one to another. Their voices were a sort of thin creaking and
hissing, but he could make out many of the words that they said. They were
talking about the dwarves. It was a sharp struggle, but worth it, said one.
What nasty thick skins they have to be sure, but I'll wager there is good juice inside.
I They'll make fine eating when they've hung a bit, said another. Don't hang
them too long, said a third. They're not as fat as they might be. been feeding
none too well of late, I should guess.
Kill them, I say, hissed a fourth. Kill them now and hang them dead for a while.
They're dead now, our warrant, said the first that they are not. I saw one a
struggling just now. Just coming round again, I should say, after a be audful
sleep. I'll show you. With that, one of the fat spiders ran along a rope till it
came to a dozen bundles hanging in a row from a high branch. Bilbo was horrified
now that he noticed them for the first time dangling in the shadows to see a
dwarfish foot sticking out of the bottoms of some of the bundles or here
and there the tip of a nose or a bit of
beard or of a hood. To the fattest of these bundles the spider went, "It is
poor old bomber, I'll bet." thought Bilbo, and nipped hard at the nose that stuck out.
There was a muffled yelp inside, and a toe shot up and kicked the spider straight and hard.
There was life in bomber still. There was a noise like the kicking of a flabby
football, and the enraged spider fell off the branch, only catching itself
with its own thread just in time. The others laughed. "You were quite right,"
they said. The meat's alive and kicking.
I'll soon put an end to that. Hed to the angry spider climbing back onto the
branch. Bilbo saw that the moment had come when he must do something. He could
knock it up at the brutes, and he had nothing to shoot with. But looking
about, he saw that in this place there were many stones lying in what appeared
to be a now dry little water course.
Bilbo was a pretty fair shot with a stone, and it did not take him long to
find a nice smooth egg-shaped one that fitted his hand cozily. As a boy, he
used to practice throwing stones at things, until rabbits and squirrels and
even birds got out of his way as quick as lightning if they saw him stoop, and
even grown up he had still spent a deal of his time at quits, dart throwing,
shooting at the wand, bowls, shooting at the wand. nine pins and other quiet
games of the aiming and throwing sort.
Indeed, he could do lots of things besides blowing smoke rings, asking
riddles, and cooking that I haven't had time to tell you about. There is no time
now. While he was picking up stones, the spider had reached Bombore, and soon he
would have been dead. At that moment, Bilbo threw. The stone struck the spider
clunk on the head, and it dropped senseless off the tree, flopped to the
ground with all its legs curled up. The next stone went whizzing through a big
wed, snapping its cords and taking off the spider sitting in the middle of it, whack, dead.
After that, there was a deal of commotion in the spider colony, and they
forgot the dwarves for a bit. I can tell you. They could not see Bilbo, but they
could make a good guess at the direction from which the stones were coming. As
quick as lightning, they came running and swinging towards the hobbit,
flinging out their long threads in all directions till the air seemed full of waving snares.
Bilbo, however, soon slipped away to a different place. The idea came to him to
lead the furious spiders further and further away from the dwarves, if he
could, to make them curious, excited, and angry all at once. When about 50 had
gone off to the place where he had stood before, he threw some more stones at
these, and at others that had stopped behind. Then, dancing among the trees,
he began to sing a song to infuriate them and bring them all after him, and
also to let the dwarves hear his voice.
This is what he sang. Old fat spider spinning in a tree. Old fat spider can't
see me. Add cop. Add a cop. Won't you stop? Stop your spinning and look for
me. Old Tom Naughty. Old big body. Old Tom Naughty can't spy me. Adacop.
Adacop. Down you drop. You'll never catch me up your tree. Not very good,
perhaps. But then you must remember that he had to make it up himself on the spur
of a very awkward moment. It did what he wanted anyway. As he sang, he threw some
more stones and stamped. Practically all the spiders in the place came after him.
Some dropped to the ground. Others raced along the branches, swung from tree to
tree, or cast new ropes across the dark spaces. They made for his noise far
quicker than he had expected. They were frightfully angry. Quite apart from the
stones, no spider has ever liked me and called that a cop. And Tom Naughty, of
course, is insulting to anybody. Off.
Bilbo scuttled to a fresh place, but several of the spiders had run now to
different points in the glade where they lived, and were busy spinning webs
across all the spaces between the tree stumps. Very soon the hobbit would be
caught in a thick fence of them all around him. That at least was the
spider's idea. Standing now in the middle of the hunting and spinning
insects, Bilbo plucked off his courage and began a new song. Lazy love and
crazy cobb are weaving wed to wind me. I am far more sweet than other meat, but
still they cannot find me. Here am I, naughty little fly. You are fat and
lazy. You cannot trap me, though you try, in your cobwebs crazy. With that he
turned and found that the last space between two tall trees had been closed
with a web. But luckily not a proper web, only great strands of double thick
spider rope run hastily backwards and forwards from trunk to trunk. Out came
his little sword. He slashed the threads to pieces and went off singing. The
spiders saw the sword, though I don't suppose they knew what it was, and at
once the whole lot of them came hurrying after the hobbit along the ground in the
branches, hairy legs waving, nippers and spinners snapping, eyes popping, full of
froth and rage. They followed him into the forest until Bilbo had gone as far
as he dared. Then, quieter than a mouse, he stole back. He had precious little
time he knew before the spiders were disgusted and came back to their trees
where the dwarves were hung. In the meanwhile he had to rescue them. The
worst part of the job was getting up onto the long branch where the bundles
were dangling. I don't suppose he would have managed it if a spider had not
luckily left a rope hanging down. With its help, though it stopped to his hand
and heard him, he scrambled up only to meet an old, slow, wicked, fat-bodied
spider, who had remained behind to guard the prisoners, and had been busy
pinching them to see which was the juiciest to eat. It had thought of
starting the feast while the others were away. But Mister Baggins was in a hurry,
and before the spider knew what was happening, it felt his sting and rolled
off the branch dead. Bilbo's next job was to loose a dwarf. What was he to do?
If he cut the string which hung him up, the wretched dwarf would tumble thump to
the ground a good way below. Wriggling along the branch which made all the poor
dwarves dance and dangle like ripe fruit. He reached the first bundle.
Feelely or Killy, he thought by the tip of a blue hood sticking out at the top.
Most lightly Feelely, he thought by the tip of a long nose poking out of the
winding threads. He managed by leaning over to cut most of the strong sticky
threads that bound him round, and then sure enough, with a kick and a struggle,
most of Feelely emerged. I am afraid Bilbo actually laughed at the sight of
him jerking his stiff arms and legs as he danced on the spider string under his
armpits, just like one of those funny toys bobbing on a wire. Somehow or
other, Feelely was got onto the branch, and then he did his best to help the
hobbit. although he was feeling very sick and ill from spider poison and from
hanging most of the night and the next day wound round and round with only his
nose to breathe through. It took him ages to get the beastly stuff out of his
eyes and eyebrows. And as for his beard, he had to cut most of it off. Well,
between them they started to haul up first one dwarf and then another and
slash them free. None of them were better off than Feelely, and some of
them were worse. Some had hardly been able to breathe at all. Long noses are
sometimes useful, you see, and some had been more poisoned.
In this way they rescued Killy, Bifur, Bofer, Dory and Nori.
Anna were of the fattest and had been constantly pinched and poked that he
just rolled off the branch and had been constantly pinned the pinch when the
spies began to come back more full of rage than ever. Bilbo immediately went
to the end of the branch nearest the tree trunk and kept back those that
crawled up. He had taken off his ring when he rescued Feelely and forgotten to
put it on again. So now they all began to splutter and hiss. "Now we see you,
you nasty little creature. We will eat you and leave your bones and skin
hanging on a tree. Ah, he's got a sting, has he? Well, we'll get them all the
same, and then we'll hang him head downwards for a day or two. While this
was going on, the other dwarves were working at the rest of the captives, and
cutting at the threads with their knives. Soon all would be free, though
it was not clear what would happen after that. The spiders had caught them pretty
easily the night before, but that had been unawares and in the dark. This time
there looked like being a horrible battle. Suddenly Bilbo noticed that some
of the spiders had gathered round old bomber on the floor and had tied him up
again and were dragging him away. He gave a shout and slashed at the spiders
in front of him. They quickly gave way, and he scrambled and fell down the tree
right into the middle of those on the ground. His little sword was something
new in the way of stings for them. How it darted to and fro. It shone with
delight as he stabbed at them. Half a dozen were killed before the rest drew
off and left Bombour to Bilbo.
Come down, come down, he shouted to the dwarves on the branch. Don't stay up
there and be netted. for he saw spiders swarming up all the neighboring trees
and crawling along the boughs above the heads of the dwarves. Down the dwarves
scrambled or jumped or dropped, 11 all in a heap, most of them very shaky and
little use on their legs. There they were at last, 12 of them counting poor
old Bomb, who was being propped up on either side by his cousin Bifur and his
brother Bofur. And Bilbo was dancing about and waving his sting, and hundreds
of angry spiders were goggling at them all round and about and above. It looked
pretty hopeless. Then the battle began.
Some of the dwarves had knives, and some had sticks, and all of them could get at
stones, and Bilbo had his Elvish dagger.
Again and again the spiders were beaten off, and many of them were killed. But
it could not go on for long. Bilbo was nearly tired out. Only four of the dwars
were able to stand firmly, and soon they would all be overpowered like weary
flies. Already the spiders were beginning to weave their webs all around
them again from tree to tree. In the end, Bilbo could think of no plan except
to let the dwarf of his ring. He was rather sorry about it, but it could not
be helped. "I am going to disappear," he said. I shall draw the spiders off if I
can, and you must keep together and make in the opposite direction. To the left
there, that is more or less the way towards the place where we last saw the
elf fires. It was difficult to get them to understand what with their dizzy
heads and the shouts and the whacking of sticks and the throwing of stones. But
at last Bilbo felt he could delay no longer.
The spiders were drawing their circle ever closer. He suddenly slipped on his
ring, and to the great astonishment of the dwarves, he vanished.
Soon there came the sound of lazy lob and at a cop from among the trees away
on the right. That upset the spiders greatly. They stopped advancing, and
some went off in the direction of the voice. Adacop made them so angry that
they lost their wits. Then Balon, who had grasped Bilbo's plan better than the
rest, led an attack. The dwarves huddled together in a knot, and sending a shower
of stones, they drove at the spiders on the left, and burst through the ring.
Away behind them now the shouting and singing suddenly stopped. Hoping
desperately that Bilbo had not been caught, the dwars went on. Not fast
enough, though. They were sick and weary, and they could not go much better
than a hobble and a wobble, though many of the spiders were close behind. Every
now and then they had to turn and fight the creatures that were overtaking them,
and already some spiders were in the trees above them, and throwing down
their long clinging threads. Things were looking pretty bad again, when suddenly
Bilbo reappeared and charged into the astonished spiders unexpectedly from the
side. "Go on, go on," he shouted. I will do the stinging. And he did. He darted
backwards and forwards, slashing at spider threads, hacking at their legs,
and stabbing at their fat bodies if they came too near. The spiders swelled with
rage and spluttered and froth, and hissed out horrible curses, but they had
become mortally afraid of sting, and dared not come very near now that it had
come back. So cursed as they would, their prey moved slowly but steadily
away. It was a most terrible business and seemed to take hours. But at last,
just when Bilbo felt that he could not lift his hand for a single stroke more,
the spider suddenly gave it up and followed them no more, but went back
disappointed to their dark colony. The dwarves then noticed that they had come
to the edge of a ring where elf fires had been. Whether it was one of those
they had seen the night before, they could not tell. But it seemed that some
good magic lingered in such spots which the spiders did not like. At any rate,
here the light was greener, and the boughs less thick and threatening, and
they had a chance to rest and draw breath. There they lay for some time,
puffing and panting, but very soon they began to ask questions. They had to have
the whole vanishing business carefully explained, and the finding of the ring
interested them so much that for a while they forgot their own troubles. Balin,
in particular, insisted on having the Gollum story, riddles and all, told all
over again with the ring in its proper place. But after a time, the light began
to fail, and then other questions were asked. Where were they? And where was
their path? And where was there any food? And what were they going to do
next? These questions they asked over and over again, and it was from little
Bilbo that they seemed to expect to get the answers, from which you can see that
they had changed their opinion of Mr.
Baggins very much, and had begun to have a great respect for him, as Gandalf had
said they would. Indeed, they really expected him to think of some wonderful
plan for helping them, and were not merely grumbling. They knew only too
well that they would soon all have been dead, if it had not been for the hobbit,
and they thanked him many times. Some of them even got up and bowed right to the
ground before him, though they fell over with the effort, and could not get on
their legs again for some time. Knowing the truth about the vanishing did not
lessen their opinion of Bilbo at all, for they saw that he had some wits, as
well as luck and a magic ring, and all three are very useful possessions. In
fact, they praised him so much that Bilbo began to feel there really was
something of a bold adventurer about himself after all, though he would have
felt a lot bolder still if there had been anything to eat. But there was
nothing, nothing at all. And none of them were fit to go and look for
anything or to search for the lost path.
The lost path. No other idea would come into Bilbo's tired head. He just sat
staring in front of him at the endless trees. And after a while they all fell
silent again. All except Balon. Long after the others had stopped talking and
shut their eyes, he kept on muttering and chuckling to himself.
Gollum. Well, I'm blessed. So that's how he sneaked past me, is it? Now I know.
Just crept quietly along, did you, Mr.
Baggins? Buttons all over the doorstep.
Good old Bilbo, Bill B. And then he fell asleep, and there was complete silence
for a long while.
All of a sudden, Dwellan opened an eye and looked round at them. "Where is
Thoren?" he asked. It was a terrible shock. Of course, there were only 13 of
them, 12 dwarves in the Hobbit. Where indeed was Storin? They wondered what
evil fate had befallen him, magic or dark monsters, and shuddered as they lay
lost in the forest. There they dropped off one by one into uncomfortable sleep,
full of horrible dreams, as evening wore to black night, and there we must leave
them for the present, too sick and weary to set guards or to take turns at
watching. Thoren had been caught much faster than they had. You remember Bilbo
falling like a log into sleep as he stepped into a circle of light. The next
time it had been Thoren who stepped forward, and as the lights went out, he
fell like a stone enchanted. All the noise of the doors lost in the night.
Their cries as the spiders caught them and bound them, and all the sounds of
the battle next day had passed over him unheard. Then the wood elves had come to
him and bound him and carried him away.
The feasting people were wood elves. Of course, these are not wicked folk. If
they have a fault, it is distrust of strangers, though their magic was strong
even in those days they were wary. They differed from the high elves of the
West, and were more dangerous and less wise. For most of them, together with
their scattered relations in the hills and mountains, were descended from the
ancient tribes that never went to ferry in the west. There the light elves and
the deep elves and the sea elves went and lived for ages and grew fairer and
wiser and more learned and invented their magic and their cunning craft in
the making of beautiful and marvelous things before some came back into the
wide world. In the wide world the wood elves lingered in the twilight of our
sun and moon, but loved best the stars, and they wandered in the great forests
that grew tall in lands that are now lost. They dwelt most often by the edges
of the woods, from which they could escape at times to hunt, or to ride and
run over the open lands by moonlight or starlight, and after the coming of men
they took ever more and more to the glowing and the dusk. Still elves they
were and remain, and that is good people. In a great cave some miles
within the edge of Murkwood, on its eastern side, there lived at this time
their greatest king. Before his huge doors of stone, a river ran out of the
heights of the forest, and flowed on and out into the marshes at the feet of the
high wooded lands. This great cave, from which countless smaller ones opened out
on every side, wound far underground, and had many passages and wide holes,
but it was lighter and more wholesome than any goblin dwelling, and neither so
deep nor so dangerous. In fact, the subjects of the king mostly lived and
hunted in the open woods, and had houses or huts on the ground, and in the
branches. The beaches were their favorite trees. The king's cave was his
palace and the strong place of his treasure and the fortress of his people
against their enemies. It was also the dungeon of his prisoners. So to the cave
they dragged Thor and not too gently, for they did not love dwarves and
thought he was an enemy. In ancient days they had had wars with some of the
dwarves whom they accused of stealing their treasure. It is only fair to say
that the dwarves gave a different account and said that they only took
what was their due, for the elf king had bargained with them to shade his raw
gold and silver, and had afterwards refused to give them their pay. If the
elf king had a weakness, it was for treasure, especially for silver and
white gems. And though his horde was rich, he was ever eager for more, since
he had not yet as great a treasure as other elf lords of old. His people
neither mined nor worked metals or jewels, nor did they bother much with
trade or with tilling the earth. All this was well known to every dwarf,
though Thoren's family had had nothing to do with the old quarrel I have spoken
of. Consequently, Thoren was angry at their treatment of him when they took
their spell off him, and he came to his senses, and also he was determined that
no word of gold or jewels should be dragged out of him. The king looked
sternly on Thoren when he was brought [clears throat] before him and asked him
many questions. But Thoren would only say that he was starving. "Why did you
and your folk three times try to attack my people at their merry making?" asked
the king. "We did not attack them," answered Thoren. "We came to beg because
we were starving." "Where are your friends now, and what are they doing?"
I don't know, but I expect starving in the forest.
What were you doing in the forest?
Looking for food and drink because we were starving.
But what brought you into the forest at all? asked the king angrily. At that
Thoren shut his mouth and would not say another word. Very well, said the king.
Take him away and keep him safe until he feels inclined to tell the truth, even
if he waits a hundred years.
Then the elves put thongs on him and shut him in one of the inmost caves with
strong wooden doors and left him. They gave him food and drink, plenty of both,
if not very fine. For wood elves were not goblins and were reasonably well
behaved even to their worst enemies when they captured them. The giant spiders
were the only living things that they had no mercy upon. There in the king's
dungeon poor Thorin lay, and after he had got over his thankfulness for bread
and meat and water, he began to wonder what had become of his unfortunate
friends. It was not very long before he discovered, but that belongs to the next
chapter, and the beginning of another adventure in which the hobbit again
showed his usefulness. Chapter 9.